today we are going to play a game I am
going to show you a tiny piece of
JavaScript code and you are going to try
to guess what the result of that code is
I Am 98 sure that most of us won't get
the answers correctly so we are also
going to take some time to understand
what the correct answer is and why by
the end of the game we might all have a
headache but we are all going to have a
deeper understanding of how JavaScript
works and how weird it is and maybe some
of the shocking things we are about to
see will help you in a coding interview
who knows please keep track of all the
correct answers and when the game is
over let me know your score on the
comment let's get started with an easy
one what do you think the output of this
code is
correct this code Returns the word fail
I'm joking I mean this code actually
does return the word fail but this is
not our first question I just wanted to
scare you a little bit our first
question is this one what is the result
of this code a false B for c not a
number the empty string and the answer
is
B and that is because JavaScript does
not want to show you an error to
accomplish this JavaScript uses a
process called type coercion this means
that it will automatically convert a
value from one type to another if it is
required to buy an operation in this
case because the minus operator can only
work with numbers the operator triggers
a numeric conversion that turns the
string into a number and that's why the
answer is 4. now that we know this what
is the result of this code a false B6 C
string 51 the not a number based on the
previous answer you may think that the
answer is B but it is not the correct
answer is C and that is because the plus
operator on JavaScript doesn't always
trigger a numeric conversion when the
plus operator is used with a number and
a string it actually converts the number
to a string and then concatenates the
strings with this knowledge it should be
easy to know the answer to our next
question what is the result of an empty
array plus an empty object a 0 b m t
array empty object as a string C object
object D not a number and the answer is
C here once again the plus operator
triggers the conversion of both array
and object to their string
representations an empty array converts
to an empty string and an empty object
converts to object object so we know
that empty array plus empty object
equals object object now let me ask you
what happens if we flip the order what
happens if we do empty object plus empty
array a object object B 0 C empty object
D not a number if you answered a object
object you are wrong the correct answer
is B zero empty object plus empty array
equals zero I'm sorry I don't make the
rules this guide does so why is empty
array plus empty object equals object
object with empty object plus empty
array equals zero the reason why is
because in this case the empty object is
not seen as an empty object it is
instead seen as an empty block of like
this so in reality the expression is
evaluated AS Plus empty array the plus
sign converts the empty array into a
number and when an empty array is turned
into a number it becomes a zero let's
practice a bit what is the result of
true plus true plus true
a true B true true true
c three D not a number the answer is Z
true plus true plus true is equals to
three this happens because when you use
the plus operator with booleans in
JavaScript converts them into numbers
true is turned into binary two which is
one which means we end up doing one plus
one plus one on the same line true minus
true will return zero since it's the
same as doing one minus one now let's
get into something more technical or
what is the return value of this
function a 1 b 2 3 C and the correct
answer is
see and that function returns three the
reason why is because of how try catch
and finally work inside the function try
block tries to return one but the
finally block always executes regardless
of whether an exception is thrown or not
and it also has the power to override
the return from try block this question
unlike the other ones isn't about some
weird JavaScript Quirk it makes sense
and it's good to know talking about
decimals what is the result of this
operation a
1.0001 B1 the answer is B that is
because JavaScript is unable to
accurately process numbers with more
than 16 digits leading it to round off
these values to one now tell me what
will this code return
a true or B false the answer is B false
this one is not a JavaScript block it
actually happens in other programming
languages computers think in binary ones
and zeros this can cause some issues
because some decimals fractions like 0.1
or 0.2 can't be exactly converted into
binary so when you tell JavaScript to
use 0.1 or 0.2 it does its best to
represent these numbers in binary but
they end up being a tiny bit more than
0.1 or 0.2 so when you add a 0.1 and 0.2
this tiny extra bit also add up making
the total slightly different than 0.3
and that's why 0.1 plus 0.2 equals 0.3
is false because the sum is in exactly
0.3 due to this tiny extra bits let's do
one that I'm sure many of you at home
will get what will this code return a
true B false the answer here is a true
as we have seen before JavaScript treat
the true as one when it comes to
mathematical operations and comparison
so when you are comparing true to one
JavaScript says they are the same
because it seems true as one based on
that what will this code return a true B
false the answer here is
B false as we know when we use two
equals JavaScript tries to help by
converting different types of data to
match each other when we use three
equals JavaScript does not make this
conversion it checks if things on both
sides are exactly the same including
their types so true equals equals equals
one is false because even though true
can be converted to one true is not
exactly the same as one because they are
different types of data one is a Boolean
value and the other is a number this is
why you should always use three equals
rather than two to stop Javascript
trying to help and do unexpected type
conversions and to finish up and this
one is for fun because I don't think you
will ever use this what is the output of
this code
banana c not a number D 11. the answer
is B this code returns banana in
JavaScript the plus sign next to a
string ring tries to convert that string
into a number in our banana case the
second a is next to a plus sign and
because we can't turn the letter A into
a number or we get not a number instead
so B plus a plus plus a plus a becomes B
plus a plus not a number plus a and
because the plus sign is used with
strings just concatenates them we get
banana in the end as you can see
JavaScript is very flexible which means
we don't get errors when we try to do
silly things like trying to add an array
to an empty object because of this we
have to be aware of the language
performing type conversions silently on
the background which may lead to bugs
that are hard to find and that is the
reason why for a long time I have not
written any JavaScript code and moved to
typescript typescript is just a better
JavaScript that will improve your
quality of life the moment you try it I
made a free 4 Hour typescript course
where we learn how it works and why it's
better than JavaScript by building a
simple blockchain it's for free so
please join right now clicking the link
below to learn about the reason I'm not
afraid of refactoring old code
typescript if you had fun today and you
learned something you did not know
before please like the video share it
with your friends and subscribe to the
channel click the link below and I will
see you there
see you on the next one bye